Andrew Sean Greer won the Pulitzer Prize
for 2018 novel called Less. So I had to
ask him, what is it like to win a
Pulitzer Prize? And his story about that
is my favorite part of the interview.
But also, we talked about his writing
process. How do you tell great stories,
develop great characters, write good
sentences. And also mantras like when
you're thinking about editing whatever
you're working on, the editor, they're
the patient, but you, the writer, you're
the doctor. And why if you want to write
great comedy, it's better [music] to be
honest than witty.
>> Where I want to start is this idea in
editing of looking for things that echo.
Tell me about that.
>> My first drafts are absolutely terrible.
Like in this new book Villa Coco, I
really wrote a lot of vignettes out of
order. I kind of put them together and
so looking it over just myself, there's
no editor yet, the first time I try to
think
what images repeat is like the easiest
thing to see. And if it's like, oh, I
seem to tell a bird story here and
there's a bird metaphor here and then at
the end there's a lot of birds in the
sky. I'm like, okay, then let's take out
all of the like porcupine stories cuz it
seems to be birds and add more birds
just because readers like a pattern but
one they can't discern. So it should
feel like it's it like you know what
you're doing. I don't know what the
theme is yet. Usually the second draft I
That's also the thing I figure out
what I'm really talking about and what
is totally off the mark has to go. Like
stories that aren't You know, I think in
Villa Coco I had this really wonderful
story about um a fraud that took place
in Venice in the 17th century and it was
hilarious but it was just not That's not
what the book is about, you know, it's
really about um what to do with your
life. It is a little bit about fraud
and crime but it was off the mark so it
had to go. So, that's also it. Looking
at
even like uh a lovely piece, if it
doesn't
rhyme with something else, because for a
novel
it all has to rhyme. It has to feel like
it's all part of the same thing.
>> Hm.
Why?
>> Because otherwise, I think for a
800-page novel it doesn't, but I think
for a 250-page novel, there should be
the feeling the reader has at the at the
end
that it was all for a reason.
You know, like if you're sitting with
your friend and they're like, "I got to
tell you the thing that happened today."
And if it's a dream they had, it is not
interesting, because there's no point to
it. But, if if they're good
storytellers, you're like, "I started
off and the milkman was late." Or
something. And you're like, "This guy
the milkman has got to be important."
The milkman doesn't end up being
important, you're kind of annoyed.
>> What I'm hearing from you is that early
on there's this certain intuitive,
almost ethereal from the subconscious
draft that gets written. And then the
conscious mind only comes in later on.
And
I don't want to infer too much, but
almost this sense of surprise that there
are themes that were there. And you're
like, "Where did they come from?" But,
they almost appeared without your
conscious will to make them appear.
>> I mean, I don't want to sound too David
Lynch about it, because that's the kind
of way that he thinks. I think he's more
magical than I am. But, I definitely the
first draft is full of I put in
everything that I could possibly use.
You know, I just spill it all on the
table. Any story or character, I'm like,
"I don't know. Is this going to be
useful?"
You know, and that I mean, they say that
you should write on whiskey and um and
edit on soda water. So, then the second
time you go through and you realize
it's true what the subconscious was
trying to get out. And all the rest that
is just sort of junk that the conscious
mind can make into a theme and a story
and something that will move a reader. I
so describe it as writing like a like a
crossword puzzle.
>> That was Nabokov. Oh, really? And I
thought he was lying cuz I thought you
can't write like a crossword puzzle.
That's nonsense. [clears throat]
But I've gotten older
and I realized that that is a really
useful way to write. So I will write a
scene. Villa Coco, I wrote a scene
that's 2/3 of the way that's about
finding a work of art.
And I'm like, I don't know where this
goes.
And then you write another scene that
just has occurred you. You know the
answer to like in a crossword puzzle.
You fill in the things you know, and
they give you clues to the other parts
that go across and slowly they all add
up because they connect to one another.
And that's how I end up writing these
books, which sounds like madness and is
madness. But it works better for me than
than planning it all out.
Either I have a nervous breakdown in the
middle because the novel has gone a
different direction than I hoped. Or um
or it feels too calculated.
And it doesn't have that organic
storytelling feel to it. So when you're
writing scene by scene, how does that
look like on a day-by-day basis? Like
are you
I don't know, maybe you're going for a
swim and you're like, "Hey, I have this
idea of a scene. Okay, I'm going to go
back to the computer. I'm going to write
out the scene." And then what I'm
imagining is almost like these different
splotches on a piece of paper that don't
like a lot of dots that haven't been
connected and kind of arranged in order.
But you're just trying to get stuff out.
Trying to get stuff out. You're just
imagining different scenes. Is that a
fair way to put it?
>> Sure. I mean, more that way is my friend
Daniel who I swim with who writes on
index cards that he puts on his dining
room table.
Which is how Nabokov wrote.
Right? He He just wrote index cards and
he did not know what they were about.
They were fully written paragraphs.
Can you imagine? It's hard to imagine
that that's true. But I've seen it in
action.
And it is true. Mine is more I know I
have a list of scenes that I'm imagining
for the book that are coming to me that
seem fun to write. And when I'm
swimming, I come up with how I'm going
to write the scene.
Meaning, what point of view, what um
details are going to be there, what
would be fun, what would be a fun way to
write the scene. Well, like you could
tell a scene of
um like backwards. You could say,
"Years later, he would look back on that
moment and remember only the goat that
was tied in the middle of the field. But
when he first arrived that morning, he
didn't see the goat at all." And so,
you're like, "Okay, I'll foreshadow
something and I'll tell it from long in
the far in the future to give it this
perspective and like freak the reader
out a little bit." Or you can just say
he walked into the room and there was no
goat there.
I mean, I read a lot of old books to see
how they used to do things because I
think a lot of these techniques are lost
in
in uh the desire to write a book. If
we're only watching TV shows, we tend to
write dialogue of people entering a
room, every single thing that happens in
that room, and then they leave the room.
Whereas actually in a book, you don't
have to do that. In fact, you don't even
have to You can say, "Like tell me the
truth." "I told her exactly what she
needed to hear." You don't have to put
the dialogue at all. You can just report
it. And so, those choices, which I think
I only know from reading a lot of books,
are the ones that I think, "What would
be fun? Oh, if I don't tell the reader
what he says." Like I just read was
reading a book now by Beryl Bainbridge
and at the end of the chapter, she says,
"I called up my mother and told her what
had happened. My mother said what she
always says."
End of scene. You're like, "Oh, I wonder
what it was." And that's kind of cool.
>> Give me other examples of
older books that you've read, things
that you've seen that are different from
how we write now that you're trying to
kind of bring into your work,
incorporate, you're getting inspired by.
>> Well, like one This is feels like a
foolish example, but it's it's it's I
think the first moment I realized that
you can do anything you want was reading
an old novel by Colette, a French
writer, and in fact that it's a novella
called Gigi, which people will know if
they've
watched the musical movie from the '50s
called Gigi.
Uh
And
at the end of it, it's about a
courtesan, she's trying to be a
courtesan, and there's a man who wants
to be her um
whatever it's called, the guy who has
the courtesan, and instead she says,
"No, I don't want to be that." And he's
very angry, and then he comes back to
the house, and he says to her mother,
"Madam Alvarez, I would love the great
honor of asking for Gigi's hand
." And Colette knew not to
say any more than that, that we knew he
was asking to marry her. And if if she
did a single word more, it would be too
sentimental. And I was like, "You can
just go   , and that's
the end? You can just leave us hanging?"
And I was stunned. I thought you had to
I thought you had to.
And then I it made me realize that the
real liberties of of of a novel
and that kind of storytelling, which is
that the narrator
and the writer
were in control, like theater. You can
there's a lot in the imagination in
theater, always, no matter how elaborate
the set is. It's still a black box.
And
it's more fun in theater if it's
actually just a black box, and the chair
turns into a train, turns into
you know, a a hotel room.
And and the novel is more like that,
that there's a lot that the reader
um invents themselves, and the more they
invent themselves, the more
tied to the book they are, and the more
they enjoy the experience. But it is the
more difficult it is the reading
experience. So, you have to decide as a
writer how difficult you want it because
a lot of readers will reject it if they
have to make up too much. Like the Beryl
Bainbridge novel I'm reading now, she
does not describe how the characters
look,
which is hard for me, cuz I love
describing how the characters look.
Um,
nor does she describe a lot of the rooms
they're in. It takes place in a theater
in the early 20 in 1948
in London, which is hard for me to
imagine what that's going to look like.
But I understand that that's part of the
fun. It's a short book. She's not going
to fill it with
extra description, and you kind of
gradually imagine the characters
yourself. It took me a while to get into
it, and now I'm really invested, because
my version of Stella is like nobody
else's. I've invented her completely.
When you think of school, what comes to
mind? For me, it was lectures, homework,
sitting at a desk. And the worst part is
it doesn't even work.
54% of Americans read below a
sixth-grade level. That's over half
of Americans. We need something new, and
that's why I'm excited to have Alpha
School as the flagship sponsor for how I
write.
At Alpha, you go to school and do all
your academics in only 2 hours per day,
so that then you can spend the rest of
the day learning life skills, like
launching a business, writing a musical,
or giving a TED Talk. You know, the kind
of things that make you a capable and
well-rounded person.
And it's working. They have academics
figured out. Alpha classes test in the
top 1% nationally, and more than 90% of
Alpha students say they love school.
Now, I used to live in Austin, where
Alpha School started, and I was
consistently blown away with what was
happening there.
I personally mentored a bunch of Alpha
students, and what stood out to me is
how much the team believes in the
potential of kids, way more than what I
ever got in school. Alpha's approach and
the success it's already having is why
it's the most talked about K-12 school
in the world right now. And it's also
where I want to send [music] my kids to
school one day. So, if you want to learn
more, go to go.alpha.school/howiwrite.
So, as you're thinking about the narr-
the narrator, the quality of the
narrator, is that something that you
kind of write down? You got this big
board, kind of like Bradley Cooper in
21, like looking over everywhere, it's
like, "Okay, this what it is." Or is it
just this really intuitive sense of
connection that you have
with your narrator and a deep intuition
about they would say this, they wouldn't
say that. They would say this, they
wouldn't say that.
>> Certainly, it's a pile of books
that I have chosen from my library that
I think my book sounds like
something that is a combination of these
books.
>> Oh, wow. And I don't know why.
And
and so I have them there and I pick them
up and read them and and tell like the
combination
creates
And I often get a lot of false starts. I
had a book called The Impossible Lives
of Greta Wells, and I must have written
the first 100 pages at of that book
three or four times.
It's like, let's change the gender of
the person. Let's tell it from a
different narrative point of view. Let's
try it first person from years later.
Let's try it present ten- You know, I
just got it wrong over and over and I
knew it.
Clearly not very quickly.
>> Mhm. But
>> Yeah, but eventually you hit it and you
know you or I know I hit it because I'm
able to produce lots of pages
easily, even if I'm going to cut them,
that they're a pleasure to write. And I
really like a first-person narrator
because you can give them a lot of
personality. Um
Less, for instance, the narrator is why
I enjoyed writing the book so much, and
the narrator is not Arthur Less.
The narrator is much smarter
and funnier. The narrator knows it's a
comedy. Arthur Less doesn't know it's a
comedy. He's actually pretty upset a lot
of the time. He's having a bad time. But
we're having a good time because the
narrator knows how the story ends.
And that's part of a comedy is a is an
understanding
that things are going to turn out okay,
and therefore it can be a funny story.
>> You're talking about voice, personality,
that distinctiveness. How do you
cultivate that?
>> Well, I read a lot of books and try to
be inspired by them without imitating
them.
Like in Less, the narrator has a very
cultivated English language capability.
You know, he I had to look up a lot of
words because he's knows more than I do,
which is really fun because you sound
really smart even though it took you
know, I had to go to the dictionary a
lot to find the kind of words that he
would use. And that is part of the humor
in that book, I think, is the language
is funny because he's over wrought.
But, that was not appropriate for Villa
Coco, which is a different narrator.
He's um
he's a much older man looking back on
his time when he was 21 or 22,
which is different than looking at
someone else.
You can make fun of yourself a lot, but
you have great empathy for that person
you used to be who you barely recognize,
and that's a different feeling, and it
was a much simpler
choice of language, and maybe less antic
storytelling.
>> What you were saying almost reminds me
of the way a designer makes a mood
board, and I've heard certain movie
makers even talk about how when they're
they'll find a playlist
that they want for the movie, and then
they'll just listen to that playlist
over and over again,
so they have a keen sense of what's the
vibe, the tenor of the story going to be
even if they can't put it to words, they
do know the feeling intimately.
>> Well, I know when I'm writing a book
that I'm
completely attuned to what is going to
help me write the book.
Meaning movies or plays or music, and I
will stop watching a movie if I'm like,
this is no good to me. You know, Jaws 3D
is not helpful.
>> [laughter]
>> Could be. I mean, I never know. It's not
like it's high or low art. It's just
what storytelling is is going to be
interesting and it's not necessarily um
just books. It's any kind of
storytelling that I go for. So, I do
start collecting those. And I do know
writers who have playlists that are what
the book is going to be. And I'm not
that kind of writer, but that makes
sense to me.
>> So, what I'm hearing, there's almost two
different ways that you would think
about consumption. One would be I'm
going to consume what's what what's
interesting to me, but now, okay, it's
time to start writing something. And now
I have this particular vector that I'm
on and I'm only going to consume things
that help me move down.
>> Yeah, it's very frustrating for my
husband who would like to watch Scream
7. And I'm like, no, we have to watch
another Bergman movie.
Which she refuses to do. And it means I
miss out on a lot of contemporary
literature
because I'm I'm it's often not helpful
to me. As wonderful as it is, it's not
what I'm working on cuz I'm more
old-fashioned, I think. So, I end up
going to a second-hand bookstore and
looking through the bookstore. And
sometimes I pick up a book I've never
heard of and I think this might be it.
Or like
this Beryl Bainbridge novel I'm reading
for my next book I'm working on. I said
I was never going to write another
novel. Clearly, I am. And uh a friend
recommended it and I'm reading it and
I'm thinking, yes, there's something
here.
There's something here.
>> What are the best bookstores?
>> I mean, I love Green Apple Books so much
because they have used books and new
books together. And that
really makes sense
to me.
Because
the the obsession um with new books uh
buy my new book, by the way. But there
But I think for for writers,
there doesn't We don't need to focus on
on everything that's just won the Booker
Prize, necessarily.
I think the problem would be that then
you would just sound like everyone else
in your
field or in your
generation. And it you What you want to
sound is just like yourself. That's the
only way to make any kind of art is to
sound more as most like yourself as
possible. And that means being open to
whatever
inspires you and not being embarrassed
by it because it's your job. You know,
you have to And you don't have to read
the newest
translation of the Odyssey because
there's a all these book clips reading
it. Although, maybe you do. That sounds
actually like a good idea.
>> Tell me more about why the old books as
opposed to the new ones.
>> Because I think a lot
varieties of storytelling, these books
that no one's reading anymore, they're
lost to us.
And there's all these inventions that
that happen
in these old novels. Old French novels
would start like Madame M
arrived at the city of V  on
the 12th of May to meet the duke. And
you're like, "What are the under dashes
about? I've never seen that before.
What's that about?" And then I think,
"Do I want like an under dash in my
novel? Will anyone understand what that
is?" No, but like in Villa Coco, I use
that kind of technique
because you don't know the narrator's
name until the end of the book. They
call him by a nickname, Jovidy, and he
has a real name.
But it's like in Daphne du Maurier's
Rebecca. People know the movie, but if
you read the book, you realize you never
hear her name. Her name is the second
Mrs. de Winter. And that's really
interesting
for the author to choose to do that. It
it um hides the character from you a
little bit, but it also there's a little
suspense.
>> It also makes it feel like maybe it's
really happened and they're trying to
cover up the information so they don't
ruin someone's life, which of course is
is nonsense. It's it's made up. And that
sort of
mixture, which we don't read anymore, um
is great to to bring back to life.
>> When you look at art history, 16th
century, 17th century, 18th century,
whatever it is,
you realize that where a piece of art
was created and when a piece of art was
created actually is more influential
than the person who made that. Like the
difference between
two artists in the 17th century is less
than the difference between art in the
17th century and art in the 21st
century. And what you realize is that
different time periods, they have a
completely different spirit. And when
it's only when you look at the old art
that you realize, "Oh my goodness,
there is such a homogeneity to the
things that we create now, not to any
fault of our own, but it's because we
live in this present age." And what I
hear you saying is, "Hey, that means
that if you're looking for new ideas,
new ways to make your work distinctive,
just go to the old stuff. They have a
completely different way of seeing and
thinking and speaking and talking about
character, story, whatever it is."
>> Yeah, absolutely. Like if you want to
write a novel that is a huge rant, you
should read Philip Roth.
>> [snorts]
>> And even if you don't like him, and I
sometimes don't, but like that is how
you learn to write a rant. Whereas like
John Updike is playful with language in
his description in a way that's very
funny to me. And I definitely was
inspired by that for Less
by Updike of all people.
>> Yeah, these are the words you always
come back to. Playfulness, joy, delight.
>> Well, I like those when I read. Dave
Eggers said that what he loves in a book
is for there to be a surprise on every
page. And he means like a surprise of
description or language or dialogue or
plot or character, any of those things.
But it should be a surprise on every
page. And I would say like Marcel
Proust, as boring as you think he is,
there's a surprise on every page.
>> Raymond Chandler, when he would write,
he had his typewriter and on something
had to happen on every single page
before the paper left the typewriter.
>> Yeah, I heard that whenever he got
bored, he would send two men with guns
through the doorway. And so you read his
read his books and you're like, I guess
he got a little bored. But he really
crafted those novels. Those are not
dashed off. Those aren't Ellery Queen
novels. Those Raymond Chandler They're
each one of them is spectacular
literature.
>> Yeah, I'm not saying you should always
write like this, but there is something
to demanding that something happens in a
short amount of time over and over. I
was just at a wedding.
And the best man gave one of the best
speeches I've ever heard. He had like 25
index cards and he just read index card,
index card, index card. And every index
card had a whole cohesive story on it.
And so just the speed, the rapid fire of
funny stuff, wow, that's a great story
was so high and it just came down to
like how he actually wrote the speech
was exactly the opposite of what
everybody else did.
>> Well, he didn't have to deal with
transitions, which can be so
are the hardest thing in a way. And so
he did away with that, which is really
smart because then you don't have to um
do the boring connective tissue, you
know? You can just get to the good
stuff. It's why in my books
someone told me or I read something
online that was like, "Will at Coca
doesn't have any chapters." And I
thought, "Sure, yes it does." And I
thought, "Oh, no it it doesn't in the
way you're thinking. It's not like Frog
and Toad are friends. It's
but it is sections separated by
like a little flower or whatever that
are sometimes really short and sometimes
really long. Then I don't have to do
those transitions. I can just have the
white space and move on to another
thing. So it doesn't have to be like
middle marched like later on in the day
or Thea thought she would pay a visit to
the tenant farmer. You know, I don't
want to do that. Well, there's a
profound point here. It's if you like to
write in a certain way, find a structure
that allows you to write in that way
rather than being constrained by how you
think writing should or needs to be. And
I think that just again goes to reading
lots of books and finding the one that
works for you, not the most popular one
out there or the one even that your
favorite book has done in, but then the
one that works for you. And I think that
maybe Kurt Vonnegut is the one who
taught me how to write in short little
things of all writers who I haven't read
in 30 years.
>> What I'm hearing from that is writing as
a way of expanding your horizon of
things that make you say, "Oh, I can
write like that. I can do that."
>> Yeah. And it takes
reading in a different way.
Um it takes
reading like a detective a little bit
and if there's something that you really
enjoyed
stopping and thinking, "How did they do
that?
How did they pull that off?" Cormac
McCarthy who does not use quotation
marks in his dialogue. That's a
particular choice. It's very distancing.
It's cold.
And that works in his writing, but it
would not work in my writing where I'm
trying to keep it warm. I like quotation
marks. Or Jose Saramago who doesn't even
separate the dialogue out from the rest
of the paragraph or give you quotation
marks. So you're doing all this work.
it's all like all in together, which is
really fun, but it it's um
it's more
fairy tale, I think. And so, seeing
which one is going to work
mostly for you personally and then for
the book you're working on. One of the
biggest things I've learned from doing
you know, 100 episodes of this now is
not for every writer, but for most
really good writers, they just have way
more to pull from than the average
writer because they've consumed so much.
I have got to watch these 100 episodes
cuz I
it's not like I don't panic
in front of the page every day. I I want
to know what these other writers said,
too, because I don't know how it's made.
But, it is true and I'm it's not like
I'm the fastest reader, but I have
trained myself to do to do this
to pay attention, to learn from all
these other things.
>> that. Training yourself to pay
attention.
>> That's what it is. It is
no longer do I get to read a book like
Lord of the Rings even and be like, "Oh,
what a fun adventures these hobbits are
auto." It's It's dangerous. I don't get
that pleasure anymore. I have to read it
and think like, "Why is this song here?
Is it
Do I like that? Like I wonder what
that's doing in the book. Is it boring
me?"
Which it used to when I was 12, but I
think now like it's part of building the
magic. You know, I would come up with
some I would be I want to know how it's
made because I have to
I'm going to have to make something
in literature later that day.
>> Well, implicit in that, too, is just
because Tolkien did it doesn't mean that
it's perfect and in every way.
Absolutely. Implicit what you're saying
is, "No, this might be a great book.
Might not be a great book, but you
definitely stood the test of time. But,
hey, I don't like this thing that
Tolkien did here. Why don't I like it?"
>> Well, like Proust, who's my favorite
writer, but I'm not imitating. In the
first volume, there's a long speech by a
church about the by a priest about the
stones of the church.
And it is so boring, and it is 50 pages
or something. And when I was teaching my
class, I said, "Proust wants you to
experience every possible human emotion,
and one of them is boredom, and you're
going to experience it in real time."
I would not do that myself. That is not
a technique that I would use. But he has
other techniques that I that I do use.
He has one way of of of creating a
sentence
where, and this is in translation, of
course, so I don't know what the
original French is, he will say like, "I
it then was awakened in me, um like a a
bird awakened by a false sun who takes
flight, that impossible thing, colon,
the past."
You know, he has this long elaborate
sentence, and then there's a colon, and
you land it. And I thought, "That is
really powerful."
And you can only do that once or twice
in a book. He does it
thousands of times in a very long book.
But I really took that away as like,
"That's a That's a great way to make a
powerful sentence."
I was talking to Lee Child, who
wrote all the Jack Reacher books, and I
asked him, "Do you outline?" He said,
"No."
And I said, "Huh, that's surprising."
And he said, "I just write." And there
was a really interesting back and forth
in the YouTube comments, of all places,
basically saying, "Okay, you guys are
missing the point. He doesn't outline,
but his mental bank of references from
reading thousands of books over the
years just means that he has this
intuitive sense of what to do. Of
course, he's outlining. He's not doing
it consciously, but there is something
going on in his brain after reading all
those books, writing all those books,
that is different from the novice who
does an outline. These are not the same
things. Just like when you're watching
um I like to watch a horror movie and
there's action and then there has to be
a moment where they're like the monster
is at bay and they're sitting in there
trapped in the graveyard where they turn
to each other and be like, "So, what was
your childhood like?" You know, you have
to have that moment and it has to happen
in probably twice in the movie to
connect the characters together. Maybe
if you're really studying you say like
it happens at exactly 35 minutes and and
at 52 minutes. But probably when you're
writing it you just think like I think
it's time for a little chill out.
You just doubt. How is the way that we
talk about character changed over the
the centuries?
Well, I know because
I went to MFA school and I see online
sometimes out of the corner of my eye
discussions of character that feel like
they're influenced by method acting.
Which is that you have to
write out everything the character has
ever done in their lives and I don't
find that to be true and I wonder what
they did
in the 19th century. Often those
characters are
they're longer books and so the
characters are built from a lot of
detail.
Maybe more like the way Stephen King
writes that he will give you a giant
pages and pages about what this sheriff
did in Texas 20 years ago.
But we don't do that that much anymore.
King does it. Anne Rice did it. Um
we're now expected I think to capture a
character instantly in a few in in
literary fiction um in a few sentences.
Which means you do have to go in
incredibly prepared.
Or
you stumble your way through the first
draft, discover the character and then
go back and remake them.
Or what I find is
the character either leaps instantly on
the page and there's no work needed
or they never do.
And you're and I have to use my skills
to make them come alive for the reader,
even though they're not alive for me.
And it's fine because that's what the
job is.
And I know how to do it.
Um
distinctive ways of talking
thinking about things more than
the way they they move. It's not giving
them a complicated past. I think we
think it always has to be like adding
and adding to their past. It's making
them a real person that you're meeting
in front of you, I think. Often, I I
don't mind being alone at a bar with a
pad of paper.
>> Ah, the best. I love sitting at the bar.
Last night, sat at the bar, had a
burger, met some characters. It's my
favorite. I mean, I really like people.
I think I life is really made up of
other people, so you might as well get
used to them.
And they're so useful for writing.
As long as you have like a pad of paper,
otherwise I'll forget. But you I can
write down not just the stories they
tell you, but like
the way they Yeah. move and talk and
whatever they're wearing and it's really
great.
>> And also, when you meet a character,
there's just these very vivid little
details about them that just encompass
who they are.
>> Yeah, and it takes nothing at all on the
page. If that person is vibrant for you,
you can put them in your book and they
don't have to
be the bartender. They could be a maid
in a 19th century book, but that person
with whatever her bug eyes and um mole
here will be alive to you and that'll
make it really easy to write them.
People who are really welcoming, people
who are not at all welcoming. I kind of
like those. I kind of like the people
who are a little off-putting.
>> Hm. Tell me more.
>> Well, I think when a bartender doesn't
want to serve you
or is gruff to you, it means that in the
scene you could turn them around a
little bit and that gives them more
action than someone's like, "Well,
hello, darling. How are you doing?
What's your name?" You're already there.
But if you have to sort of persuade them
and in real life, I often never persuade
them.
>> [laughter]
>> They're never never into me. Of course
you want something to happen in the
dialogue, but you don't have to. You can
have something happen in the background.
You can have a cat in the bar that's
trying to make its way across behind the
bottles to the other side. And if it
makes it to the other side, you feel
like something happened in the scene
even if it's undetermined. It something
has to happen
in every
portion, but it doesn't have to
be what you think it is.
>> Why do you keep coming back to surprises
like the thing in every scene?
>> You want them to turn the pages.
And you want them even in a literary
fiction, I think, because people
they won't read it if they don't turn
the pages.
And yet what they're coming for isn't
plot. What they're coming for actually
paragraphs of beauty and wisdom and
poetry, but they're not going to read
just huge blocks of those. Or
I think. So, you have to do use these
other techniques to get them to turn the
pages so they get to those blocks of
poetry. And then when they finish the
book, they're like, "You have got to
read this book and it has this beautiful
paragraph." Something they would never
have gotten to if you hadn't put it in a
diamond heist.
>> Is creating drama and suspense something
that you go for?
>> Yeah, for sure. I don't think of myself
as a
uh
a Hitchcock genius of suspense, right?
But I think there's a lot of ways to
create suspense
um
narratively
that aren't necessarily about like a
bomb about to go off in 5 minutes. You
know, you can even start the novel
saying like the
I died on the 24th of December. I cannot
explain to you how I'm able to
communicate this to you from the other
world, but I will start at the beginning
and you're like, oh my god, he's going
to die? How does this go? And then
you're fine. In fact, there's a novel
called The Posthumous Memoirs of Bras
Cubas, which is like a Brazilian
masterpiece.
>> Bras Cubas. Bras Cubas. Bras Cubas.
>> And it starts that way and you're like,
what? And this is a novel from
the early 20th century and it does this
thing at the beginning. He's speaking
from the afterworld. He's like, it's too
complicated to explain how, but I have
to tell you about my life.
And it's the posthumous memoirs.
>> Right.
>> And it's in Portuguese and we've never
heard of it and it's so crazy.
And I like those. That's surprising to
me.
>> What's this uh throw with your left-hand
device that you
>> Yeah. This was great. I was in graduate
school and I was very
pretentious and show-offy. I was like
young
writer. I wanted to show off what I
could do and I would write these obscure
stories with aliens or, you know,
17th century aristocrats and robots and
just to try to be postmodern or I don't
know what I was doing.
And I everyone hated them and I thought
they asked me to write a realistic story
and I said, all right, I'll show them.
And I wrote a story about a gay man and
a lesbian who get married in the 1960s
as beards for each other and their
marriage over the next 30 years and how
they really become each other's true
love in a way. I brought it in, everyone
loved it and I was like, I showed them.
Like they don't know that I was just
kidding. And my professor, William
Kittredge, a Western writer, like cowboy
Western writer,
took me into his
and he told me
some baseball story I don't recall.
Who's a famous left-handed pitcher?
>> Whitey Ford.
>> Whitey Ford. And all he said was Whitey
Ford always throwed with through with
his left hand.
And
it took me a while to understand like
if
you're good at this
>> Yeah.
>> Andy
you're showing off with all this other
stuff, but this is what you're good at.
You're good at emotion.
And it's not shameful
to do what you're good at. In fact, it's
the only thing there is to do.
And maybe
I I wanted to be the cleverest writer in
America and I just was not going to be.
I was going to be
the the a vulnerable writer. And that's
the last thing you want to be at 23.
But
I really understood
what he was saying to me. And that is
the first short story I ever published.
But I think about it a lot. Um
about less.
You know, that that book was a comic
novel and it turned out I was good at
that, which I did not know.
And my last two books, Villa Koko is a
comic novel.
And I think, boy, am I allowed to write
these still? There's not a lot of
literary comic novels out there and I
think
Whitey Ford
pitch with his left hand. You get to
pitch with your left hand. If you're
if this is what you're good at, the
pages are coming, if you're enjoying it,
if readers are enjoying it there that is
what the whole
point is.
>> Yeah, what came to mind for me is there
there's four ways of thinking about
competence. Unconsciously incompetent,
consciously incompetent then you can be
consciously competent at something and
then you can be unconsciously competent
at something. And I think a lot of the
times the things that we're consciously
competent at, we've had to work for.
We're like, I've worked really hard to
get good at that. But I think often the
things that were unconsciously competent
at, they've come so natural to us that
we actually just don't even admire those
things in others. We don't admire them
in ourselves. So then we don't actually
do those things and a lot of
the way that people in any craft can do
better is just to
be
conscious of the things that they're so
naturally competent at and do those
things and actually learn to appreciate
what those things are.
>> I That's exactly it. That it feels like,
well, it's easy. Anybody can do that.
And
it is not true anybody can do that. That
is just what you can do. And when it
feels easy, it doesn't feel like it's
art.
But it is.
It is. It doesn't have to be
white-knuckling it through.
It can be a a a pleasure. You know, I it
is writing is really hard. I said that
before. It's not.
But writing Villa Coca was a pleasure.
And I learn I'm old enough now to say
like, I'm just going to have um a great
time doing what I think I'm good at.
It feels easy, but I'm aware that like I
have peers who don't write this way. I
don't know if they can write this way.
So I'm going to
This is my little niche, you know? This
is perfect for me.
>> From reading about this, it seems like
one of the things that you picked up on
is that a lot of comedy comes from
tragedy and rather than talk about it
as, oh, this is so sad, that the tragedy
can then become funny.
>> Yes. I I would say you have to think
about the hardest things for you.
And see if you are capable of making it
into a funny story. And if you are,
I mean, Paul Beatty wrote a book um The
Sellout, which is about slavery
coming back.
And that is not a funny subject, but he
makes it really funny. It's the hardest
thing for him and he was able to make it
any one the Booker Prize and things.
And
and I think I learned that lesson in
less because I was writing a very
serious book about a middle-aged gay man
in San Francisco and it was such a
tedious self-pitying book. I thought I
can't write this.
And then
I've told this story before that I went
swimming, the miracle thing,
but really in a desperation about what
to do with this book.
And I just thought, well, what the hell,
I'll just make fun of him instead.
And opened every door because I was
writing about stuff that was really hard
for me.
You know,
there is one point at the beginning of
the book where it says, "Arthur Less was
the first homosexual ever to grow old."
Which I think is a funny sentence
because the word homosexual is like
hilarious.
And rather than say he felt like the
oldest homosexual, it just says he was
the oldest as a homosexual.
And what that is really about is that
everyone else in the generation above
him, almost all the men died of AIDS.
And so he had never had any
um
any example of how to turn 40, 50, 60,
which I don't. And it's a track It's one
of the greatest tragedies I've witnessed
in my life just to see all those men die
and I escaped it because I'm just young
enough. But it's a funny sentence. But I
have learned that you have to You can
only You have to be really quick
by touching on those really hard things
in a comedy.
Or at least for me.
That you touch on them and you want to
make the reader realize we're having
fun, but we're really talking about
something serious. And what I'm doing is
I'm leading you through the fire and I'm
distracting you while we go through this
hard thing and then we'll realize we're
on the other side of it.
But once in a while you have to look
around and see what we're going through.
And this was Joan Rivers who said this.
She's telling a Helen Keller story, like
a ridiculous Helen Keller story, and
someone yells, "That's not funny."
And she says, "My mother was deaf."
What do you think comedy is about?
Comedy is about taking us to the hardest
things of our lives all together and
looking at it together. You're stupid.
>> [laughter]
>> The other thing about comedy is just the
old cliche, it's about timing, which
means there's a lot of revision
just in the
the timing of small things. How does
that work on the page? It's very clear
to me how that works
when you're seeing stand-up or
something. How does it work on the page
with timing? You have to work with the
words to delay something.
You play it out or you have to make it
go faster. You add less. There's right
at the end. I was with my friend Daniel,
who's very funny writer. And
I think he'd told me like, "Your last 20
pages need to be like eight."
>> Hm.
>> And I just cut and cut and cut. I was
like, "I can't make it any shorter
because he's in Japan and he needs to
take a plane to San Francisco to go back
for the final scene." And he said,
"Andy, you don't have to write him
getting on a plane. You can write
next paragraph  he stood
at his house. I needed it faster. It
wasn't funny
or moving unless I kept picked up the
pace and that is done grammatically.
>> [laughter]
>> In comedy, how much of great comedy
writing for you comes from it being your
first pass and you just had it in your
heart and you just
plopped it out on the page versus the
revision, the revision, trying to get
that right?
>> The funny stuff is all in the first
pass.
I got to say.
>> Why is it true for comedy that it's in
the first pass, but then you talk so
much about the importance of editing and
other parts for a novel.
>> I'm not a witty person. I'm not a quick
wit. I'm very much someone who thinks of
the right thing to say, you know,
l'esprit de l'escalier, on the way out
of the party.
>> Oh, I wish I'd said that.
>> But that's only like 2 minutes later.
So, at the writer's speed, 2 minutes is
not very long. So, I'm able to get it in
the page and I can have fun.
However, in revision, I'm
there I'm able to see
where I'm like, "Oh, I set up a joke
without knowing it, and now I see where
I can make it land."
In Less Is Lost, there's a whole scene
he's out in the desert with these
hippies and they built a universe
appreciation platform that looks really
rickety. And then later, he takes
blueberries he didn't know have
mushrooms in them and he goes on a trip.
And And in the original version, he woke
up in a teepee naked. And
on the final version, I was like, "No,
he has to wake up on the universe
appreciation platform. Why did I put it
there if not?" It's much funnier if he's
naked on a universe appreciation
platform and he cannot get down.
Like that's better than just a teepee.
And I I wrote it for myself. It is all
there. I just had to
later see it. And that happens all the
time, that I have set up a joke for
myself, but I have not finished it.
>> You were talking earlier about learning
from
other writers throughout history?
What comedy writers have you learned
from that you've then incorporated into
your writing?
>> These are maybe not going to sound like
comedy writers
to people, but
in the '50s and '60s,
literary writers
who we think of as great important
people, they also wrote comedies. That
was just
part of the thing. Updike was a comedic
writer. And Philip Roth, definitely a
comedic writer, and Saul Bellow, and
playwright Thornton Wilder wrote farces,
and all of that felt like normal part of
being a
also a serious writer. So, I actually
enjoy
reading them.
And there's a lot of British writers I
enjoy that are
not as laugh-out-loud funny, but are
have a certain charm
from the early 20th century.
American readers don't read these books.
Here's a good example of reading things
that other people don't read. Nancy
Mitford novels.
No one's heard of her. Gerald Durrell.
Famous in England for a book called My
Family and Other Animals. And never
heard of him. For Villa Coco, these are
the books I looked at for books that
were
a very gentle kind of comedy.
Harmless, but like just constantly
again, delighted by them.
>> Talk to me about the transition
into lesson into being a comedy writer
and
losing your British publisher.
>> Oh, yeah.
>> [laughter]
>> Um I don't know why I laughed.
I
>> Cuz tragedy leads to comedy.
>> Yeah. Well, I wrote last I got to tell
you the book before that, The Impossible
Lives of Greta Wells,
barely reviewed,
certainly not purchased by readers, and
I felt like I it felt like it was
beneath notice to me. I'm I'm too
sensitive to these things. And I thought
it's all over I'm as a writer like I've
>> That was your fourth fifth book at that
time?
>> Fifth book. Fourth novel. And I thought,
well, that's it, you know, I'm an old
man
46 or something, and
I've written a book that is beneath
notice, and I guess I'm just out of the
club.
Which liberated me
to write anything I wanted,
you know? And so, I wrote this comedy. I
just assumed no one was ever going to
read it. I put in things that are way
too personal that people should not know
about my life
that are there and I'm glad I did
because it turns out people don't care
about my life. They enjoy the a novel,
you know, per se. Usually when a a novel
is published in America, then you get a
British publisher and it's just they
publish it there as well and I did for
all of my books with the same publisher,
Faber. And they de clined to publish
Less
based on
book sales of my last of the book
before. Not on the idea of like we're
investing in you for a a lifetime. No,
they were kicking me free. But so did 11
other British publishers. I never found
a British publisher for Less. It came
out in the United States. No British
publisher
until
the day after I won the Pulitzer Prize.
Which was like 10 months later. You
know, it was like significantly a long
time had passed. And then they all
wanted to publish it.
Can you imagine a more satisfying
>> [laughter]
>> So what is it like winning the Pulitzer?
>> It was
>> Like what is the day like when you find
out, okay, oh my goodness, I just won
and then what happens in the aftermath
of that?
>> I was working in Tuscany as director of
an artist residency.
>> Yeah, I saw that place. Look cool.
>> It was pretty cool. There were um some
dogs that were roaming free. Margaret
Atwood was coming, so that was a big
deal and I was like, I think these pugs
shouldn't be pooping all over the dining
room table when Margaret Atwood is here.
So I'm in the floor, not the table.
And so I bought diapers from China that
have suspenders cuz pugs have no waist
and you can't they won't stay on a
diaper, I discovered. So I was training
the pugs to wear diapers that evening.
And I um
put them to bed,
and it was like 10:00.
I'm
There's a time difference. That's an
important part of the story. And also,
we had no cell reception. So, I wasn't
looking at my cell phone the way we do
now, cuz there was no no point in
looking. So, that was my evening was
taken up by
the pugs and the diapers. And then, my
boyfriend was there, and he showed me
his phone,
and it was the San Francisco Chronicle.
Someone had sent it to him that says,
"Local author wins Pulitzer Prize."
Andrew Sean Greer.
But, I didn't know when the Pulitzer
happened. I didn't It's April 18th, by
the way. But, I didn't know that. It was
just another day in in, you know,
And so, I just said, "That is not true."
>> [laughter]
>> It was very clearly not true to me. And,
um,
but I did look at my phone. I was back
in cell phone range, and I had a million
text messages, and they're all like
fireworks, dancing Spanish lady, you
know, like clown fish, like not very
helpful texts. High heel. And, but I did
have a lot of calls from Michael Chabon.
Good friend. He had won the Pulitzer
Prize in I think 2001. And I thought,
"Okay, if there's some sort of fraud or
weird a fake rumor, yeah, he will tell
me the truth."
Cuz I'm like, "Don't get me worked up
about something that's clearly not
true."
And I've been fooled in the past.
So, I called him,
and he said,
"Andy, do you not know?"
And I said, "I don't know what you're
talking about, Michael." He said, "Am I
the first person to tell you?" And he
he told me I had won the Pulitzer Prize.
And he said,
"Let me tell you two things. There is no
downside,
and now you can write any book you want
to."
>> Let's go.
>> That liberated me to completely enjoy
myself.
>> It's like tenure for writers.
>> Yeah.
And then, um, Michael Cunningham called
me,
who had won the Pulitzer Prize for The
Hours, and he said, "All All the writers
who had won the Pulitzer Prize all
contacted me who are still living."
That's what happens.
They all contact you. So, it's Donna
Tartt and Jhumpa Lahiri, and like
writers I didn't know, and you suddenly
feel like you're accepted. It was an
incredible experience over those days to
feel part of something.
And Michael Cunningham said, "Do not
waste any time worrying about whether
you deserve it."
Which I had not occurred to me yet.
But, I thought, "Okay, that's not my
job. I was not on that committee. I got
it, and I'm not going to worry about
whether
a comic novel deserves to win a Pulitzer
Prize. That's not my, you know,
position."
>> The thing that really stands out about
that story is that you wrote less
in
a state of some combination of
hopelessness, despair,
"Oh my goodness, I just don't have it
anymore."
>> Again, that's where comedy comes from.
I'm sure Seinfeld would tell you that.
He's He's the one who said, "Comedy is
when you decide it's a funny story."
Life is not funny.
You just decide.
What happened today to you is is awful
and miserable,
but you decide it's a funny story when
you tell it to your friends at the bar,
and they laugh, and you feel, "Okay, I'm
over it."
You know?
And that was a low point in my life when
I wrote Less. And to be
to win that prize for it? I can't tell
you. That was That was supposed to be a
book no one
would even read. And then, it was a best
seller for a year.
>> What is your
self-conception as an artist, as a
writer? What How do you think about what
that means, and what it is that you're
trying to do?
>> That's a good question. It's funny to to
to like say I'm an artist. I do think of
myself that way. I think it's from going
to artist residencies and they're being
with like real artists, painters, and
like sculptors and things, and they
definitely see writers as their peers.
And so I'm I'll take it.
I wouldn't have called myself that
before, but I certainly with my other
writer friends, we
you know, our lives are in a way devoted
to art. We're we're making things that
just may not be popular.
They're popular by accident, honestly.
Like Less, that wasn't accidentally
popular.
But I was happy with that book
before it was published because I
thought I have made the thing in my head
as closely as I possibly can, and I am
That's all I wanted to do. And that is
the artistic sensation. Is it there's a
compulsion, and if you're able through
great effort to to make it, and it
sounds like madness. It sounds like um
Richard Dreyfuss in Close Encounters of
the Third Kind where he's had a vision
and he builds the mountain out of mashed
potatoes at the kitchen table. That kind
of feels like what it is. Like it's
madness to live with someone like that,
and Terry Carr leaves him, but that is
it. There's something in your head and
you have to make it, and what are the
right materials, and what I'm going to
do, and no one understands me.
They won't understand me until I've made
it, and then you make it, and often they
still don't understand you. But
sometimes
but the but the pleasure comes from
having having done it as closely as
possible. That's I remember that in
Less. I was so happy
before publication came out. I thought,
you know, it'll be great to get good
reviews or or whatever happens, but
because I thought it would never be a
success anyway, I just wanted that
artistic sensation.
>> What you learn from the painters?
>> I learned
do you have to let
the lacquer dry.
>> [laughter]
>> Their process is so similar to writing a
novel that it's wonderful to talk to
them.
That they will say things like
I spent all day painting tiny little
flowers in the upper right-hand corner.
And I'll be like, I know exactly what
you mean.
Because I spent all day replacing the
word dog with the word cat.
You know, it's something that doesn't
feel like art.
>> Wait, I want to stop you there. I think
that that's
so profound that a lot of the work of
writing
of being an artist, what people imagine
is you're like Jackson Pollock, you
know, you got your bucket of paint
splashing the paint on the page, you
know, like whatever it is. And it's this
like think of a singer just getting
after it. But no, actually a lot of the
work is super specific,
maybe technical, maybe intellectual, and
what comes from it is art. But actually
what you're doing on a day-by-day basis
doesn't feel like the
cultural understanding of what an artist
is.
>> Yeah, that big inspiration, it just
pours I mean, that's lovely when that
happens.
And then there is but revision does not
feel like that. Revision feels very
technical
to me. Revision is like this scene isn't
working. I have to technically figure
out how to fix it. Whether I cut it,
whether it goes somewhere else.
You know, again looking at the the the
rhyming and mirroring in the book, this
scene belongs here because
um on page 30, there's a scene with the
donkey. So 30 pages from the end there
should be a scene with the donkey and
it'll match it. How do I Now I have to
reconnect everything to make it make
sense, which does not feel
inspirational. It's very technical. Tell
me more about the painters. They will
say um I lacquered I put on a whole coat
of lacquer and so I just had to sit and
wait for it to dry. And I thought that
makes sense. It's like when I polish a
whole scene and I can't
I I I I I can't look at it again to to
um adjust it or critique it. I have to
let it
hang out and leave my mind for a little
while. And over and over there are
things that make sense. Especially that
when you talk to painters or any visual
artists, photographers care about not
their subjects, even if their subjects
are like naked people in front of them.
They care about light.
And painters
they don't care about their subject.
They care about paint. That absolutely
makes sense to me. It sounds insane. But
painters will talk about the texture of
the paint and the color and how it's
applied and how it dries and whether you
use linseed oil and they're you know,
all these technical things. And I think
about words.
>> Well, there's a Picasso quote that I
really like. When art critics get
together, they talk about form and
structure and meaning. When artists get
together, they talk about where you can
buy cheap turpentine.
>> Exactly.
>> It's the deep specifics. I mean, also
just hanging out with artists here,
they're always talking about money.
>> Well, yes.
>> People like they talk about money more
than the finance people talk about
money. It's like there's this extreme
pragmatism of what they're doing, which
has really surprised me.
>> Right. You would think they're like,
"Who care I for money or fame or riches?
I'm just going to be wearing this
smock."
>> need money so that I can make my art.
Where do I find money? You know what I
mean?"
>> Yeah, if they're a good professional,
they find grants or they have gallerists
and there's practical things to do for
all of that. And for writers, it's true,
too. You know, you wonder how Less came
about? I was a travel writer for years
and years and I would come to New York.
I remember I was like, "I have to make
some money somehow." And I had a friend
who was an intern at Travel and Leisure,
a former student. And I said, "I want
you to introduce me to your editor." She
said,
"He won't take a meeting with just some
writer." And I said, "Doesn't matter. I
just want you I want to go to lunch with
you and have you introduce me as I'm
passing by." And I dressed in the
loudest colors I possibly could
so that "Behold, this is my friend Andy.
Hi, he's on the phone. That's it." I
thought I was like, "One day they'll be
be meeting. They'll be like, 'You know,
so-and-so can't write this piece.'" And
my friend will say, "Well, what about my
friend Andy? Who's he? You know, he was
the guy in the bright clothes." Sure.
And that's exactly what happened.
But I had to be really cunning.
>> [laughter]
>> You other You have to eat.
>> Which leads me to ask,
what career advice do you have for
writers?
>> I highly recommend life experiences.
I highly recommend them. They're um
And it either means like a a different
interesting career as your day job. Um
one that might provide you some stories.
Interactions with lots of people.
You don't have to be a big drinker go to
bars, but that's an example of like
paying attention. I would say replace
your iPhone with an pad of paper exactly
the same size. And when you were bored
waiting for the bus,
pay attention to what is around you.
But the career advice is you're going to
have to make money. You'll probably
never make money from your writing. So,
find something or someone
to support you
at a minimum level. If you have fancy
tastes, then
um good luck to you.
But the other thing to know is that
there is no champagne room that you're
finally invited into where all the VIPs
are sitting around and say, "Well done,
my good and faithful servant." And there
there's no heaven. There's just writers.
You know, there's I can tell you that
like maybe the champagne room was Donna
Tart emailing me with pictures of her
own pug.
But like
there's no room. There's no separate
existence. You're still the hard work.
And um
and and no private club. Every writer is
interesting to me no matter what they
are in their career unless as long as
they're honest about talking about their
work. It's all interesting.
>> Take me back to when you were a travel
writer and you would go to different
places and only write about I think it
was places you've been and experiences
that you actually had.
>> Yeah, I had notebooks. And less and less
is lost those were my rules is that I
couldn't make up anything. Certainly for
travel writing I didn't want to make up
anything. Plenty of people do.
But
I didn't want it to be for instance the
white guy making up stuff about Vietnam.
Because it'll probably tap into some
orientalist fantasy of mine. Where am I
getting this made up stuff? And it'll be
you know, nonsense and offensive. So I
I also I was alone in Vietnam in a
restaurant that took two hours to bring
me my food. So I took a lot of notes.
>> And what do you look at? Like if you're
in a restaurant in Vietnam
what sorts of things are you writing
down on the page?
>> I mean everything. I am writing down the
brand of the air conditioning unit in
the corner.
I'm writing down I remember one
restaurant where there was a dog. They
the the food was made up front. And um
the chef was out there boiling bones and
he would shoo the dog into the back and
the dog would go down and sit down and
look at me. Then the waitress would come
and she would shoo the dog up to the
front and he would sit there until he
got shooed back. It just felt like a
metaphor for something. Maybe something
Buddhist. Like when would he be released
from this? You know, I remember a parrot
in a cage, you know, talking and talking
and talking and one restaurant and those
are all details that made it into my
novel cuz they feel like they're about
something.
They feel poignant
and funny.
>> If you were describing this room, you
had a notepad, what were the first three
things that you would
>> Well, my favorite thing is that window,
which is at such an angle, but they have
remade the window to make it look
normal, but they can't hide the fact
that something's happened over time. It
looks like one of the houses in Snow
White, doesn't it?
>> Yeah.
>> They're kind of droopy.
Looks like my apartment in Venice, which
is so wobbly that I put my
rolling chair down and it rolls like
Poltergeist across the floor.
>> Yeah.
>> [laughter]
>> But those it makes it human. I'm like
humans made this. That's what evidence
I'm I'm looking for evidence that it's
human.
What
>> is the difference between great travel
writing and crappy travel writing?
>> Well, you can see crappy travel writing
if you ask AI to write anything. Because
it's um
it's so full of cliches.
When I am a travel writer and also when
I was writing Less Than Zero Than Zero,
I looked for the thing you would not
expect in that place. A way to make you
rethink. Like in Morocco
there's a point where Les goes to a ski
resort.
Which I was taken to.
>> Right.
>> And I just thought that is
>> Mountains?
>> In the Atlas Mountains. I was like, I
was not expecting a ski resort in
Morocco. Of course there's a ski resort.
They have mountains.
But you know, we have I
you want to get away from the cliche. I
had to write about camels. I had to
write about Bedouins, but I needed
something to widen the view of that
country.
>> So cliche is what I'm hearing is the
first thing. There's a lot of cliche in
travel writing. What you don't want to
do is lean into those cliches. But
the superficial way to read your advice
is write about the opposite way of the
cliche, which is also probably the
>> be crazy cuz it's not representative of
the place.
>> Exactly.
>> I think of one place we stopped and
there was um
a little boy who had a a
a little chick that had been dyed bright
pink.
All the chicks had been dyed different
colors and he was selling them
because they were brightly colored. And
of course, you don't I won't want that.
It's going to turn into a chicken.
But there was something amazing about
it. I thought, "Whose idea was this?
This is someone's idea. It must work."
Someone's buying these dyed chickens.
Tourists maybe. You know, like
it's something that's neither a cliche
nor the opposite. It is something
utterly itself.
And and therefore interesting and and
again
I think in travel writing, you for me,
I'm writing about the human beings.
Um I'm not a nature writer particularly.
I'm a I write about people. So, I'm so
interested in how the people vary.
And how they're very much like us.
Actually, that's what of course you find
when you travel. That's a cliche in and
of itself. So, you try to hide that. But
you do find that people are poor and
kind everywhere. And in in very specific
ways.
>> With AI, are you like, "I will not touch
it." or you incorporate it a little bit?
What is your relationship with it?
>> It's very simple. I am suing a number
I'm a representative plaintiff in a
number of suits against these companies.
So, I'm not allowed to use AI.
>> Or talk about it.
>> Or talk [laughter] about it. All right.
>> Or else you're going to be deposed and
you don't want to be deposed.
>> No, that's so boring. I'll I'll I'll
stay out of court.
>> Um poetry, why do you keep it by by you
when you're writing?
>> Because I think that they are the ones
who go down in the mines and get the
jewels and bring them up. It's it's like
Indiana Jones. They do all the hard
work, And bring out the golden idol, and
I'm like the French bad guy who's like,
"Once again, Mr. Jones, what you have
fought for is now mine." I take their
discoveries, which are narrative
discoveries, language discoveries. I
learn every time I read poems, just like
reading old books. They have
because they're shortening everything
down and condensing and mixing things
and using
end breaks. They're um
line breaks. Um
It It's just constant invention for a
prose writer.
Not always, but often. Both
elevating your sense of what's possible
and expanding your sense of what you can
do as well. Yeah, and it's not to sound
poetic. It is
um
I'm trying to I'm in a I'm in a poetry
Zoom club that's been going for years
every Friday, and we meet for an hour,
and it takes us months to get through a
poem. M- I I left
the club. Um we'd started a poem by
Wallace Stevens, and I was gone for a
month, and I came back and they were on
stanza four.
Because we're really most of it's poets,
but there's also novelists and that I
look there are
prose
answers to prose
problems I have in poetry. How do you
read a poem? Like if we were sitting
down to read a poem at lunch, and I
said, "Hey, can Can we spend 30 minutes
on this?" What would we do?
>> You read it all loud, and then you go
and then you
then you think, "What's standing out to
me?" Like and let me examine that more
closely.
Why is that interesting to me? What's
going on there? What am I resistant to?
What am I enjoying?
Usually now I can tell in terms of
prose answers, I can tell right away. Um
There's a book called The Others by
Matthew Rohrer. It's a long series of
poems, but it's a prose piece. It's
stories within stories. And but not just
in the Scheherazade way because it's a
poem, it teaches me something else about
how within a story you can have someone
telling a story, which in Villa Coco
happens a lot. There's this old woman, a
baronessa, who's telling these crazy
stories, and I had to figure out how to
work those in. I found them really fun,
but I realized people might find them
distracting cuz it's not the plot
anymore.
And don't you hate it when they're
suddenly telling you a 40-page story and
you're like, "But what what happened to
the cowboys, you know?" So, I learned
from that book about that. Let's finish
here with this advice from Daniel
Handler.
The editor is the patient and you are
the doctor.
That is one of the wisest things he ever
said to me, and he has a lot of wisdom.
What does it mean? We think
that um the book is the patient, the
editor is the doctor, and they know
they're going to say, "Nurse, here's
what I need you to do." and that you do
it, but that is not true.
The editor is the patient.
They're the reader. They know they're
feeling things, and they can come It's
like a patient who comes in and says,
"Doctor, my arm hurts. I'm sure it's arm
cancer."
You, the writer, say,
"It's There's no such thing as arm
cancer, but the arm hurts. That's
important. I will figure it out." The
editor will not know the answer because
it's in your head.
The thing you want to make, they have no
access to it. And a good editor will not
tell you specifically what to do. They
will just tell you where it hurts.
And
you could have a lot of people read your
book, and if they consistently say where
it hurts, ignore Please ignore the
advice they give you. It'll really throw
you off, especially in a in a workshop.
But they're right about what's not
working. I've said this in my classes,
you know, there will be a story that is
about a middle-aged couple having
marriage problems and then there's a
mermaid that appears at the end. And
everyone will say, "Cut out the mermaid.
It doesn't fit." And I will say,
"Or, more mermaid." Right? The problem
is it doesn't fit.
But the solution is not necessarily cut
out the mermaid.
Uh how about we prepare for the mermaid
by more mermaid, commit to the mermaid,
and less married couple in a vague mer-
you know, like that's not as
interesting.
The first instinct will be to to make
the work mediocre.
And you as a writer have to think,
"Should I actually commit to the thing
that's strange and putting the reader
off?" And the first instinct will end up
making the work more mediocre a lot of
the time. Why? Because it is getting rid
of the thing that doesn't fit.
Like for Less, my editor is the best in
the world, Lee Boudreaux, God bless her,
but she did suggest to me that I should
cut the ending, which has a kind of
revelation in it.
She said, "We don't We've had such a
good time. We don't want to risk
spoiling it for readers who will be put
off."
And I said,
"I understand. It doesn't work yet.
I will make it work."
And I spent most of my time changing the
rest of the novel so that the ending
would land properly, which was a lot of
work, but luckily I was
developed enough to know to to that her
solution was definitely the easiest one,
but it was not the right one.
Thank you. That's so fun to talk about
that stuff.
>> I'm glad you enjoyed it.
>> No one talks about that in interviews.
>> [laughter]
>> They want to know where I grew up. Yeah.
>> I'm glad you enjoyed it.